Avery Family Photographs Collection
Avery Memorial Association
Avery Family Photographs Collection
Circa 1870-2011
Avery family
Coll. 1
2 linear feet; 3 boxes, 3 albums
Avery Memorial Association
Photographs and other graphic materials related to the Avery family of the Groton, Connecticut area. These include images of Avery family members, family reunions, historical reenactments, and buildings associated with the family, as well as the move and reconstruction of the Ebenezer Avery House.
Restrictions
Collection open for research by appointment only.
Acquisition Information
Various donations over time.
Biography
The Avery family of Connecticut traces its American origins to Christopher Avery (circa 1616-1679) who settled in Gloucester, Massachusetts and relocated to Connecticut in 1665.
James Denison Avery was the Town Clerk of Groton, Connecticut in 1894. On Friday night, July 20, 1894, his house, the old Avery family homestead (referred to as the Hive of the Averys) was burned to the ground by the sparks from a passing train. The wave of nostalgia after the destruction of the homestead led to the formation of the Avery Memorial Association in 1894. James Denison Avery was the first President of the Association until his death on January 26, 1897.
The Association was incorporated in 1895 by a special act of the Connecticut legislature. The names on the Association's Charter are as follows: James D. Avery, Cyrus Avery, Christopher L Avery, Helen Avery of Groton, Allen Avery of Stonington and Elroy M Avery of Cleveland, Ohio.
The Hive homestead site by the railroad tracks was deeded to the Avery Memorial Association by James Denison Avery. A large obelisk-shaped monument was erected on the site. On Friday, July 20, 1900, the monument was dedicated. It is located at the corner of Poquonnock Hill Rd and U.S. Highway 1 in the town of Groton.
The Ebenezer Avery House was built sometime in the 1750s by Parke Avery for his son Ebenezer. The house was used to shelter some of those wounded in the September 6, 1781 Battle of Groton Heights at Fort Griswold in Groton. In 1970, R. Stanton Avery of San Marino, California bought the house and gave it to the Association along with funds to help in the restoration. Ground was broken on June 23, 1971 to move the house from its original location at the corner of Thames and Latham Streets to the grounds of Fort Griswold State Park. The house itself was turned over to the State of Connecticut in a letter dated April 27, 1973 (signed by Governor Tom Meskill). Members of the Avery Memorial Association contributed 18th-century period furnishings, which the Association owns. The house was opened to the public on November 29, 1973.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is primarily composed of photographs, as well as a few postcards and other graphics, related to the Avery family of the Groton, Connecticut, area. Buildings and places with family associations, such as the Hive of the Averys, Old Mystic Baptist Church, the Avery House in Ledyard, a church in Ipplepen, England and the move and reconstruction of the Ebenezer Avery House in Groton are among the sites and features depicted. Images of individual family members, family reunions, the Avery window in Groton Congregational Church and reenactments of the Battle of Groton Heights are also included in the collection.
Arrangement
Photographs are housed in three boxes and three albums. In Box 1, they are arranged in folders organized by accession number and corresponding folder number.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Avery family; Avery Memorial Association; Buildings--Repair and reconstruction; Dwellings; Family reunions; Groton Heights, Battle of, Conn., 1781; Historic house museums; Historical reenactments; Moving of buildings, bridges, etc.; Groton (Conn.); New London County (Conn.); Photographs; Portrait photographs
- Inventory
  - AMA.2008.217, 1870-1894; Colored photo of Hive. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AMA.2008.426, 1905; 200th anniversary of Old Mystic Baptist Church card with photo. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AMA.2008.494, undated; Notecard sketch of Church in Ipplepen England where Christopher Avery was married. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AMA.2008.518, undated; 34 photos of the Battle of Groton Heights reenactment. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AMA.2008.519, 1898-1901; Photo of Julia Geer Avery and son Billings Avery in front of the Avery Homestead on Avery Hill Road, Ledyard. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AMA.2008.520-525, 1970-1975; AMA.2007.520 – nine Photos and negatives of Ebenezer Avery house being reconstructed, 1970-1971; AMA.2007.521 - postcard showing the Groton Monument; AMA.2007.522 - photo of house being rebuilt, snow visible; AMA.2007.523 - three negatives of the interior of the house, two of the kitchen and one of the corner cupboard, May 1975; AMA.2007.524 - negative of the Avery House under construction; AMA.2007.525, four negatives of the house being rebuilt. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - AMA.2007.526-527, AMA.2007.535.01-03, AMA.2007.539, AMA.2007.553, AMA.2008.389, 1895-2007; AMA.2007.526 – older lady; AMA.2007.527 – Belton Allyn Copp IV (1920-2011) with his Aunt Emily Avery Copp Burrows (1888-1964); AMA.2007.553 – bookmark of St. Dunstan and envelope; AMA.2007.539 – postcard of Groton Congregational Church; AMA.2007.535.02-03 – two photos of individual men, with note to “see Bible”; AMA.2007.535.01 AMA.2008.389 – pencil drawing of Congregational Church, done by S. Avery for the foundation; Photo of church in England – no accession number. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - AMA.2007.529, 1970-1973; 42 photos enclosed in album pages depicting the Ebenezer Avery House, mostly during the move to its current location. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AMA.2007.530, AMA.2007.433, 1974-2007; Four photos of family reunion/annual meeting, 1974 and other years. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AMA.2007.531-532, AMA.2007.534, 1978-2000; 15 photos of family reunions/annual meetings for July 1978, July 1995, July 2000, including 2007.531, 2007.532 and 2007.534 (some duplicates). (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Battle of Groton Heights reenactment photographs, 1981; 117 photos, enclosed in album sheets, of 1981 historical reenactment of Battle of Groton Heights, Fort Griswold. (Box 2)
  - Battle of Groton Heights reenactment photographs, 1994-2011; Avery family reunions, 1994, 1996, 1999, 2003, 2006, 2007, 2011; Avery window in Groton Congregational Church; group photo of Alice Sheriff, Jane Chambers and Stephanie Lantiere. (Box 3)
  - AMA.2007.465, 1971; Photograph album 1: Photos of Ebenezer Avery House move to Fort Street. (Volume 1)
  - AMA.2007.468, undated; Photograph album 2: Amos G. Avery photos of cemetery, Ebenezer Avery house, reunion, reenactments, Hive, 100th anniversary of Avery Memorial Association, paintings of Avery family members. (Volume 2)
  - AMA.2007.467, 2000; Photograph album 3: July 2000 family reunion/annual meeting, with identifying captions. (Volume 3)